{
    "lessons": [
        {
            "id": "lesson1",
            "title": "lesson 1",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which language is known as the 'mother of all programming languages'?",
                    "options": [
                        "C",
                        "Python",
                        "Java",
                        "JavaScript"
                    ],
                    "correct": "C"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which symbol is used to end a statement in C language?",
                    "options": [
                        ";",
                        ":",
                        ".",
                        ","
                    ],
                    "correct": ";"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "What does HTML stand for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Hyper Trainer Marking Language",
                        "Hyper Text Markup Language",
                        "High Text Marking Language",
                        "Hyper Text Marketing Language"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Hyper Text Markup Language"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which of the following is a backend programming language?",
                    "options": [
                        "CSS",
                        "Python",
                        "HTML",
                        "React"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Python"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which operator is used for comparison in most languages?",
                    "options": [
                        "=",
                        "==",
                        "===",
                        ":"
                    ],
                    "correct": "=="
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "In JavaScript, which keyword is used to declare a variable?",
                    "options": [
                        "var",
                        "int",
                        "declare",
                        "def"
                    ],
                    "correct": "var"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which data structure works on the principle of LIFO?",
                    "options": [
                        "Queue",
                        "Stack",
                        "Array",
                        "Linked List"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Stack"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which of these is a dynamically typed language?",
                    "options": [
                        "C",
                        "C++",
                        "Java",
                        "Python"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Python"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which programming paradigm does Java follow?",
                    "options": [
                        "Procedural",
                        "Functional",
                        "Object-Oriented",
                        "Markup"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Object-Oriented"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "What is the correct file extension for Python files?",
                    "options": [
                        ".pyth",
                        ".pt",
                        ".py",
                        ".p"
                    ],
                    "correct": ".py"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson2",
            "title": "lesson 2",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a primitive data type in Java?",
                    "options": [
                        "int",
                        "boolean",
                        "String",
                        "char"
                    ],
                    "correct": "String"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "What will be the output of: 5 % 2 ?",
                    "options": [
                        "2",
                        "1",
                        "0",
                        "5"
                    ],
                    "correct": "1"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which loop is guaranteed to execute at least once?",
                    "options": [
                        "for loop",
                        "while loop",
                        "do-while loop",
                        "foreach loop"
                    ],
                    "correct": "do-while loop"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which keyword is used to exit a loop immediately?",
                    "options": [
                        "exit",
                        "stop",
                        "break",
                        "return"
                    ],
                    "correct": "break"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "In Python, what is the output of: type(3.0)?",
                    "options": [
                        "int",
                        "double",
                        "float",
                        "decimal"
                    ],
                    "correct": "float"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which of these is a mutable data type in Python?",
                    "options": [
                        "tuple",
                        "list",
                        "str",
                        "int"
                    ],
                    "correct": "list"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "What does the 'else' block in a loop execute?",
                    "options": [
                        "When loop condition is true",
                        "When loop finishes without break",
                        "Always at the end",
                        "When syntax error occurs"
                    ],
                    "correct": "When loop finishes without break"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which operator is used for logical AND in most programming languages?",
                    "options": [
                        "&&",
                        "&",
                        "AND",
                        "||"
                    ],
                    "correct": "&&"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "In JavaScript, what is the result of: '5' + 2?",
                    "options": [
                        "7",
                        "52",
                        "Error",
                        "NaN"
                    ],
                    "correct": "52"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which function is the entry point of every C program?",
                    "options": [
                        "start()",
                        "init()",
                        "main()",
                        "program()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "main()"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson3",
            "title": "lesson 3",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which keyword is used to define a function in Python?",
                    "options": [
                        "func",
                        "function",
                        "def",
                        "define"
                    ],
                    "correct": "def"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "What is the index of the first element in an array in most programming languages?",
                    "options": [
                        "1",
                        "0",
                        "-1",
                        "Depends on the language"
                    ],
                    "correct": "0"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "In Java, which keyword is used to create an object?",
                    "options": [
                        "create",
                        "class",
                        "new",
                        "object"
                    ],
                    "correct": "new"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a benefit of using functions?",
                    "options": [
                        "Code reusability",
                        "Easier debugging",
                        "Better organization",
                        "Slower execution"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Slower execution"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which data structure is best for storing a collection of elements of the same type?",
                    "options": [
                        "Array",
                        "HashMap",
                        "Stack",
                        "Queue"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Array"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "In object-oriented programming, which concept allows using the same method name with different parameters?",
                    "options": [
                        "Encapsulation",
                        "Inheritance",
                        "Polymorphism",
                        "Abstraction"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Polymorphism"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "What is the correct syntax for calling a function named 'myFunc' in C?",
                    "options": [
                        "call myFunc;",
                        "myFunc();",
                        "function myFunc;",
                        "run(myFunc);"
                    ],
                    "correct": "myFunc();"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "In JavaScript, how do you declare an array?",
                    "options": [
                        "var arr = [];",
                        "array arr;",
                        "arr = array();",
                        "let arr = array[];"
                    ],
                    "correct": "var arr = [];"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which OOP concept bundles data and methods together?",
                    "options": [
                        "Encapsulation",
                        "Polymorphism",
                        "Inheritance",
                        "Composition"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Encapsulation"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which of these is a constructor in C++?",
                    "options": [
                        "A function with same name as class",
                        "A static function",
                        "A global function",
                        "A void method"
                    ],
                    "correct": "A function with same name as class"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson4",
            "title": "lesson 4",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which OOP concept allows a class to use properties and methods of another class?",
                    "options": [
                        "Encapsulation",
                        "Inheritance",
                        "Abstraction",
                        "Polymorphism"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Inheritance"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "In Java, which keyword is used to inherit a class?",
                    "options": [
                        "inherits",
                        "super",
                        "extends",
                        "implements"
                    ],
                    "correct": "extends"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which keyword is used in Java to inherit an interface?",
                    "options": [
                        "extends",
                        "implements",
                        "interface",
                        "use"
                    ],
                    "correct": "implements"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which OOP concept focuses on showing only essential details and hiding implementation?",
                    "options": [
                        "Encapsulation",
                        "Inheritance",
                        "Abstraction",
                        "Polymorphism"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Abstraction"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "What is true about abstract classes?",
                    "options": [
                        "They cannot have any methods",
                        "They can only have private methods",
                        "They cannot be instantiated",
                        "They must contain only static methods"
                    ],
                    "correct": "They cannot be instantiated"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "In C++, how is multiple inheritance achieved?",
                    "options": [
                        "Using the keyword implements",
                        "Using multiple base classes in declaration",
                        "Using virtual functions only",
                        "C++ does not support multiple inheritance"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Using multiple base classes in declaration"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which OOP concept allows different classes to define methods with the same name?",
                    "options": [
                        "Abstraction",
                        "Encapsulation",
                        "Polymorphism",
                        "Inheritance"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Polymorphism"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "In Java, an interface can contain:",
                    "options": [
                        "Only abstract methods",
                        "Abstract and default methods",
                        "Only variables",
                        "Constructors"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Abstract and default methods"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which of these best describes method overriding?",
                    "options": [
                        "Two methods with same name but different parameters",
                        "Subclass provides its own version of a method",
                        "Defining multiple methods in same class",
                        "Calling multiple methods at once"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Subclass provides its own version of a method"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which OOP principle is most closely related to real-world hierarchy (Parent → Child)?",
                    "options": [
                        "Polymorphism",
                        "Abstraction",
                        "Inheritance",
                        "Encapsulation"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Inheritance"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson5",
            "title": "lesson5",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which data structure works on the principle of FIFO?",
                    "options": [
                        "Stack",
                        "Queue",
                        "Array",
                        "Tree"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Queue"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which operation adds an element to the top of a stack?",
                    "options": [
                        "push",
                        "pop",
                        "enqueue",
                        "dequeue"
                    ],
                    "correct": "push"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which operation removes an element from a queue?",
                    "options": [
                        "push",
                        "pop",
                        "enqueue",
                        "dequeue"
                    ],
                    "correct": "dequeue"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "What is the main advantage of a linked list over an array?",
                    "options": [
                        "Faster access to elements",
                        "Dynamic memory allocation",
                        "Uses less memory",
                        "Always faster performance"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Dynamic memory allocation"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "In a singly linked list, each node contains:",
                    "options": [
                        "Data only",
                        "Data and pointer to next node",
                        "Data and pointer to previous node",
                        "Only pointers"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Data and pointer to next node"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which data structure is used in function call/recursion?",
                    "options": [
                        "Queue",
                        "Stack",
                        "Heap",
                        "Graph"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Stack"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which hashing technique resolves collisions by linking elements at the same index?",
                    "options": [
                        "Open addressing",
                        "Chaining",
                        "Double hashing",
                        "Linear probing"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Chaining"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "In a circular queue, what happens when rear reaches the end of array?",
                    "options": [
                        "Queue overflows",
                        "Rear moves to front if space is available",
                        "Queue is destroyed",
                        "All elements are deleted"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Rear moves to front if space is available"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which of these is not a linear data structure?",
                    "options": [
                        "Array",
                        "Stack",
                        "Graph",
                        "Queue"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Graph"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "What is the time complexity of accessing an element in a HashMap (average case)?",
                    "options": [
                        "O(1)",
                        "O(n)",
                        "O(log n)",
                        "O(n log n)"
                    ],
                    "correct": "O(1)"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson6",
            "title": "lesson 6",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "What is the time complexity of binary search (average case)?",
                    "options": [
                        "O(1)",
                        "O(n)",
                        "O(log n)",
                        "O(n log n)"
                    ],
                    "correct": "O(log n)"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a comparison-based sorting algorithm?",
                    "options": [
                        "Merge Sort",
                        "Quick Sort",
                        "Counting Sort",
                        "Heap Sort"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Counting Sort"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which sorting algorithm is the fastest on average for large datasets?",
                    "options": [
                        "Bubble Sort",
                        "Quick Sort",
                        "Selection Sort",
                        "Insertion Sort"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Quick Sort"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "What is the worst-case time complexity of Bubble Sort?",
                    "options": [
                        "O(1)",
                        "O(n)",
                        "O(n^2)",
                        "O(log n)"
                    ],
                    "correct": "O(n^2)"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which searching algorithm works efficiently only on sorted arrays?",
                    "options": [
                        "Linear Search",
                        "Binary Search",
                        "DFS",
                        "BFS"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Binary Search"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which sorting algorithm is stable?",
                    "options": [
                        "Merge Sort",
                        "Quick Sort",
                        "Heap Sort",
                        "Selection Sort"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Merge Sort"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which of these is the best case for Insertion Sort?",
                    "options": [
                        "Array already sorted",
                        "Array reverse sorted",
                        "Array random order",
                        "All cases same"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Array already sorted"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "What is the space complexity of Merge Sort?",
                    "options": [
                        "O(1)",
                        "O(n)",
                        "O(log n)",
                        "O(n^2)"
                    ],
                    "correct": "O(n)"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which algorithm uses the divide-and-conquer technique?",
                    "options": [
                        "Quick Sort",
                        "Merge Sort",
                        "Binary Search",
                        "All of the above"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All of the above"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which algorithm is used in Dijkstra’s shortest path?",
                    "options": [
                        "Greedy Algorithm",
                        "Dynamic Programming",
                        "Backtracking",
                        "Divide and Conquer"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Greedy Algorithm"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson7",
            "title": "lesson 7",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which SQL command is used to retrieve data from a database?",
                    "options": [
                        "INSERT",
                        "UPDATE",
                        "SELECT",
                        "DELETE"
                    ],
                    "correct": "SELECT"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which of these is a NoSQL database?",
                    "options": [
                        "MySQL",
                        "MongoDB",
                        "PostgreSQL",
                        "Oracle"
                    ],
                    "correct": "MongoDB"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which of the following is a Firebase feature?",
                    "options": [
                        "Authentication",
                        "Realtime Database",
                        "Firestore",
                        "All of the above"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All of the above"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which SQL keyword is used to sort results?",
                    "options": [
                        "SORT BY",
                        "ORDER BY",
                        "GROUP BY",
                        "RANK"
                    ],
                    "correct": "ORDER BY"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which of these is a primary key?",
                    "options": [
                        "A unique identifier",
                        "A foreign key",
                        "A duplicate column",
                        "A random field"
                    ],
                    "correct": "A unique identifier"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which database stores data in documents as JSON?",
                    "options": [
                        "MySQL",
                        "MongoDB",
                        "PostgreSQL",
                        "SQLite"
                    ],
                    "correct": "MongoDB"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Firebase Firestore is what type of database?",
                    "options": [
                        "Relational",
                        "Graph",
                        "Document",
                        "Key-Value"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Document"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which SQL command is used to remove a table?",
                    "options": [
                        "DELETE",
                        "DROP",
                        "REMOVE",
                        "CLEAR"
                    ],
                    "correct": "DROP"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which of these is NOT a database management system?",
                    "options": [
                        "MySQL",
                        "SQLite",
                        "React",
                        "Oracle"
                    ],
                    "correct": "React"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which Firebase database allows real-time updates?",
                    "options": [
                        "Firestore",
                        "Realtime Database",
                        "Both",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Both"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson8",
            "title": "lesson 8",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "REST APIs use which protocol?",
                    "options": [
                        "HTTP",
                        "FTP",
                        "SMTP",
                        "SSH"
                    ],
                    "correct": "HTTP"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "GraphQL was developed by?",
                    "options": [
                        "Google",
                        "Facebook",
                        "Microsoft",
                        "Amazon"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Facebook"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "JSON stands for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Java Source Object Notation",
                        "JavaScript Object Notation",
                        "Java Syntax Output Node",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JavaScript Object Notation"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which HTTP method retrieves data?",
                    "options": [
                        "POST",
                        "GET",
                        "PUT",
                        "DELETE"
                    ],
                    "correct": "GET"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "GraphQL queries return?",
                    "options": [
                        "Only requested data",
                        "All database",
                        "XML",
                        "CSV"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Only requested data"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which format is mostly used in REST API?",
                    "options": [
                        "XML",
                        "CSV",
                        "JSON",
                        "TXT"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JSON"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "HTTP status code 404 means?",
                    "options": [
                        "OK",
                        "Not Found",
                        "Server Error",
                        "Unauthorized"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Not Found"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which is NOT a REST principle?",
                    "options": [
                        "Stateless",
                        "Cacheable",
                        "Layered System",
                        "Mutable Session"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Mutable Session"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "GraphQL mutation is for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Reading",
                        "Writing/Updating",
                        "Sorting",
                        "Debugging"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Writing/Updating"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which tool is used to test APIs?",
                    "options": [
                        "VS Code",
                        "Postman",
                        "React",
                        "Git"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Postman"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson9",
            "title": "lesson 9",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which command initializes a new Git repository?",
                    "options": [
                        "git start",
                        "git init",
                        "git new",
                        "git create"
                    ],
                    "correct": "git init"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which command shows commit history?",
                    "options": [
                        "git log",
                        "git show",
                        "git history",
                        "git commits"
                    ],
                    "correct": "git log"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which file stores ignored files in Git?",
                    "options": [
                        ".gitignore",
                        ".gitconfig",
                        "ignore.txt",
                        "config.json"
                    ],
                    "correct": ".gitignore"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which branch is created by default?",
                    "options": [
                        "main",
                        "master",
                        "dev",
                        "default"
                    ],
                    "correct": "main"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which command stages changes?",
                    "options": [
                        "git push",
                        "git add",
                        "git commit",
                        "git stage"
                    ],
                    "correct": "git add"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which command uploads code to remote?",
                    "options": [
                        "git fetch",
                        "git push",
                        "git merge",
                        "git upload"
                    ],
                    "correct": "git push"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which command downloads changes from remote?",
                    "options": [
                        "git fetch",
                        "git pull",
                        "git clone",
                        "git sync"
                    ],
                    "correct": "git pull"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which command creates a new branch?",
                    "options": [
                        "git branch new",
                        "git checkout -b",
                        "git init branch",
                        "git make"
                    ],
                    "correct": "git checkout -b"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which command merges branches?",
                    "options": [
                        "git merge",
                        "git pull",
                        "git sync",
                        "git push"
                    ],
                    "correct": "git merge"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Git is a?",
                    "options": [
                        "Programming language",
                        "Database",
                        "Version control system",
                        "Compiler"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Version control system"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson10",
            "title": "lesson 10",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which HTML tag is used for tables?",
                    "options": [
                        "<div>",
                        "<table>",
                        "<form>",
                        "<ul>"
                    ],
                    "correct": "<table>"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which tag defines an image?",
                    "options": [
                        "<pic>",
                        "<img>",
                        "<src>",
                        "<image>"
                    ],
                    "correct": "<img>"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which attribute specifies a link URL?",
                    "options": [
                        "src",
                        "href",
                        "url",
                        "link"
                    ],
                    "correct": "href"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Semantic tag for navigation?",
                    "options": [
                        "<nav>",
                        "<section>",
                        "<aside>",
                        "<main>"
                    ],
                    "correct": "<nav>"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which input type is for email?",
                    "options": [
                        "text",
                        "mail",
                        "email",
                        "password"
                    ],
                    "correct": "email"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which tag is used for video?",
                    "options": [
                        "<vid>",
                        "<video>",
                        "<media>",
                        "<play>"
                    ],
                    "correct": "<video>"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "HTML5 introduced?",
                    "options": [
                        "<article>",
                        "<section>",
                        "<footer>",
                        "All"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which tag makes a checkbox?",
                    "options": [
                        "<checkbox>",
                        "<input type='checkbox'>",
                        "<check>",
                        "<box>"
                    ],
                    "correct": "<input type='checkbox'>"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which tag defines a list item?",
                    "options": [
                        "<li>",
                        "<ol>",
                        "<ul>",
                        "<item>"
                    ],
                    "correct": "<li>"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which meta tag sets page encoding?",
                    "options": [
                        "<meta charset>",
                        "<meta encode>",
                        "<meta utf>",
                        "<meta type>"
                    ],
                    "correct": "<meta charset>"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson11",
            "title": "lesson 11",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which property changes text color?",
                    "options": [
                        "font-color",
                        "text-color",
                        "color",
                        "background"
                    ],
                    "correct": "color"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which unit is relative to parent?",
                    "options": [
                        "px",
                        "em",
                        "cm",
                        "in"
                    ],
                    "correct": "em"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "CSS Grid property for columns?",
                    "options": [
                        "grid-template-columns",
                        "grid-cols",
                        "flex-cols",
                        "columns"
                    ],
                    "correct": "grid-template-columns"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which position keeps element fixed?",
                    "options": [
                        "absolute",
                        "fixed",
                        "relative",
                        "sticky"
                    ],
                    "correct": "fixed"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which pseudo-class is for hover state?",
                    "options": [
                        ":focus",
                        ":hover",
                        ":active",
                        ":link"
                    ],
                    "correct": ":hover"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Flexbox direction row?",
                    "options": [
                        "flex-direction: row",
                        "row: flex",
                        "display: row",
                        "align: row"
                    ],
                    "correct": "flex-direction: row"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which sets background image?",
                    "options": [
                        "background-img",
                        "background-image",
                        "img",
                        "image"
                    ],
                    "correct": "background-image"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "CSS variable is declared with?",
                    "options": [
                        "@",
                        "--",
                        "$",
                        "#"
                    ],
                    "correct": "--"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Media queries used for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Animations",
                        "Responsive design",
                        "Colors",
                        "Grids"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Responsive design"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which property adds shadow?",
                    "options": [
                        "text-shadow",
                        "box-shadow",
                        "shadow",
                        "outline"
                    ],
                    "correct": "box-shadow"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson12",
            "title": "lesson 12",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which keyword declares a constant?",
                    "options": [
                        "var",
                        "let",
                        "const",
                        "static"
                    ],
                    "correct": "const"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which method converts JSON to object?",
                    "options": [
                        "JSON.stringify()",
                        "JSON.parse()",
                        "toObject()",
                        "parseJSON()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JSON.parse()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which operator checks both value & type?",
                    "options": [
                        "==",
                        "===",
                        "=",
                        "!="
                    ],
                    "correct": "==="
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which array method adds element at end?",
                    "options": [
                        "push()",
                        "pop()",
                        "shift()",
                        "unshift()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "push()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Arrow functions were introduced in?",
                    "options": [
                        "ES5",
                        "ES6",
                        "ES7",
                        "ES8"
                    ],
                    "correct": "ES6"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which keyword handles errors?",
                    "options": [
                        "if",
                        "catch",
                        "throw",
                        "try-catch"
                    ],
                    "correct": "try-catch"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which method filters array?",
                    "options": [
                        "map()",
                        "filter()",
                        "reduce()",
                        "find()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "filter()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which function delays execution?",
                    "options": [
                        "setInterval()",
                        "setTimeout()",
                        "delay()",
                        "sleep()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "setTimeout()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "typeof null is?",
                    "options": [
                        "null",
                        "object",
                        "undefined",
                        "boolean"
                    ],
                    "correct": "object"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which scope is block-scoped?",
                    "options": [
                        "var",
                        "let",
                        "function",
                        "global"
                    ],
                    "correct": "let"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson13",
            "title": "lesson 13",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "React was developed by?",
                    "options": [
                        "Google",
                        "Facebook",
                        "Microsoft",
                        "Amazon"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Facebook"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "JSX stands for?",
                    "options": [
                        "JavaScript XML",
                        "Java Syntax Extension",
                        "JSON XML",
                        "Java Standard"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JavaScript XML"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which hook is for state?",
                    "options": [
                        "useEffect",
                        "useState",
                        "useReducer",
                        "useContext"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useState"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "React components return?",
                    "options": [
                        "HTML",
                        "JSX",
                        "CSS",
                        "JSON"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JSX"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which command creates React app?",
                    "options": [
                        "npx create-react-app",
                        "npm start react",
                        "react new",
                        "yarn react"
                    ],
                    "correct": "npx create-react-app"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Props are?",
                    "options": [
                        "Mutable",
                        "Immutable",
                        "Variables",
                        "Functions"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Immutable"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which renders UI?",
                    "options": [
                        "render()",
                        "print()",
                        "display()",
                        "show()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "render()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "useEffect is used for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Styling",
                        "Side Effects",
                        "Props",
                        "State"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Side Effects"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which method updates state in class components?",
                    "options": [
                        "updateState()",
                        "this.setState()",
                        "change()",
                        "modify()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "this.setState()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "React is?",
                    "options": [
                        "Framework",
                        "Library",
                        "Language",
                        "Compiler"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Library"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson14",
            "title": "lesson 14",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "State in React is?",
                    "options": [
                        "Immutable",
                        "Mutable",
                        "Static",
                        "External"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Mutable"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Props are passed from?",
                    "options": [
                        "Child to Parent",
                        "Parent to Child",
                        "Anywhere",
                        "Global"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Parent to Child"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which hook manages state?",
                    "options": [
                        "useState",
                        "useEffect",
                        "useContext",
                        "useReducer"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useState"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Props are?",
                    "options": [
                        "Arguments",
                        "Variables",
                        "Functions",
                        "Objects"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Arguments"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which is used for default props?",
                    "options": [
                        "setProps",
                        "defaultProps",
                        "initProps",
                        "startProps"
                    ],
                    "correct": "defaultProps"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Props cannot be?",
                    "options": [
                        "Changed",
                        "Read",
                        "Passed",
                        "Accessed"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Changed"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "State updates cause?",
                    "options": [
                        "Nothing",
                        "Re-render",
                        "New Component",
                        "Crash"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Re-render"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which type are props?",
                    "options": [
                        "Read-only",
                        "Writable",
                        "Mutable",
                        "Static"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Read-only"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Props drilling means?",
                    "options": [
                        "Deep passing props",
                        "Deleting props",
                        "Updating state",
                        "Sharing hooks"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Deep passing props"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Best way to avoid prop drilling?",
                    "options": [
                        "useEffect",
                        "useContext",
                        "useState",
                        "useReducer"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useContext"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson15",
            "title": "lesson 15",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Hooks were introduced in?",
                    "options": [
                        "React 14",
                        "React 15",
                        "React 16.8",
                        "React 17"
                    ],
                    "correct": "React 16.8"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which hook handles side effects?",
                    "options": [
                        "useEffect",
                        "useState",
                        "useReducer",
                        "useMemo"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useEffect"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which hook for state?",
                    "options": [
                        "useState",
                        "useRef",
                        "useMemo",
                        "useCallback"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useState"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which hook stores mutable ref?",
                    "options": [
                        "useMemo",
                        "useRef",
                        "useEffect",
                        "useContext"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useRef"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which hook memoizes value?",
                    "options": [
                        "useMemo",
                        "useEffect",
                        "useCallback",
                        "useState"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useMemo"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which hook memoizes functions?",
                    "options": [
                        "useState",
                        "useCallback",
                        "useEffect",
                        "useMemo"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useCallback"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which hook shares data globally?",
                    "options": [
                        "useEffect",
                        "useReducer",
                        "useContext",
                        "useState"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useContext"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "useReducer is alternative to?",
                    "options": [
                        "useState",
                        "useEffect",
                        "useRef",
                        "useMemo"
                    ],
                    "correct": "useState"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Custom hooks are?",
                    "options": [
                        "Functions",
                        "Classes",
                        "Props",
                        "Variables"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Functions"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Hooks can be used in?",
                    "options": [
                        "Class components",
                        "Functional components",
                        "Both",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Functional components"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson16",
            "title": "lesson 16",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "TypeScript is developed by?",
                    "options": [
                        "Facebook",
                        "Google",
                        "Microsoft",
                        "Amazon"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Microsoft"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "File extension for TypeScript?",
                    "options": [
                        ".js",
                        ".ts",
                        ".tsx",
                        "Both .ts & .tsx"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Both .ts & .tsx"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "TypeScript is a superset of?",
                    "options": [
                        "Python",
                        "C++",
                        "JavaScript",
                        "Java"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JavaScript"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which keyword defines type?",
                    "options": [
                        "type",
                        "interface",
                        "var",
                        "struct"
                    ],
                    "correct": "type"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which supports OOP in TS?",
                    "options": [
                        "Class",
                        "Struct",
                        "Module",
                        "Namespace"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Class"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which type means any value?",
                    "options": [
                        "unknown",
                        "any",
                        "void",
                        "never"
                    ],
                    "correct": "any"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which type means no value?",
                    "options": [
                        "null",
                        "undefined",
                        "void",
                        "never"
                    ],
                    "correct": "void"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which utility makes properties optional?",
                    "options": [
                        "Partial",
                        "Readonly",
                        "Pick",
                        "Record"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Partial"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which keyword is used for inheritance?",
                    "options": [
                        "extends",
                        "inherits",
                        "super",
                        "base"
                    ],
                    "correct": "extends"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which type never returns?",
                    "options": [
                        "never",
                        "void",
                        "null",
                        "undefined"
                    ],
                    "correct": "never"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson17",
            "title": "lesson 17",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Node.js is built on?",
                    "options": [
                        "V8 Engine",
                        "Java VM",
                        ".NET",
                        "PHP"
                    ],
                    "correct": "V8 Engine"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which module handles file system?",
                    "options": [
                        "fs",
                        "http",
                        "path",
                        "os"
                    ],
                    "correct": "fs"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which module creates server?",
                    "options": [
                        "http",
                        "url",
                        "net",
                        "dns"
                    ],
                    "correct": "http"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "npm stands for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Node Project Manager",
                        "Node Package Manager",
                        "Network Package Manager",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Node Package Manager"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which command initializes npm?",
                    "options": [
                        "npm start",
                        "npm init",
                        "npm install",
                        "npm run"
                    ],
                    "correct": "npm init"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which keyword imports modules?",
                    "options": [
                        "require",
                        "import",
                        "include",
                        "load"
                    ],
                    "correct": "require"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which keyword exports modules?",
                    "options": [
                        "exports",
                        "output",
                        "module",
                        "send"
                    ],
                    "correct": "exports"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which method reads a file?",
                    "options": [
                        "fs.read()",
                        "fs.readFile()",
                        "fs.getFile()",
                        "file.read()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "fs.readFile()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which function runs async code?",
                    "options": [
                        "setTimeout()",
                        "delay()",
                        "async()",
                        "await()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "setTimeout()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which file defines dependencies?",
                    "options": [
                        "package.json",
                        "index.js",
                        "server.js",
                        "config.json"
                    ],
                    "correct": "package.json"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson18",
            "title": "lesson 18",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Express.js is a?",
                    "options": [
                        "Framework",
                        "Library",
                        "Language",
                        "Compiler"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Framework"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which command installs Express?",
                    "options": [
                        "npm install express",
                        "npm add express",
                        "yarn express",
                        "node install express"
                    ],
                    "correct": "npm install express"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which method handles GET?",
                    "options": [
                        "app.get()",
                        "app.post()",
                        "app.use()",
                        "app.fetch()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "app.get()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which method handles POST?",
                    "options": [
                        "app.get()",
                        "app.post()",
                        "app.put()",
                        "app.send()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "app.post()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Middleware is used for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Routing",
                        "Handling requests",
                        "Error handling",
                        "All"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which method starts server?",
                    "options": [
                        "app.run()",
                        "app.listen()",
                        "app.start()",
                        "app.begin()"
                    ],
                    "correct": "app.listen()"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which package allows CORS?",
                    "options": [
                        "cors",
                        "axios",
                        "helmet",
                        "express-cors"
                    ],
                    "correct": "cors"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which module makes HTTP requests?",
                    "options": [
                        "axios",
                        "fetch",
                        "request",
                        "All"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which status code is success?",
                    "options": [
                        "200",
                        "201",
                        "204",
                        "All"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which method updates data?",
                    "options": [
                        "PUT",
                        "PATCH",
                        "Both",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Both"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson19",
            "title": "lesson 19",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "JWT stands for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Java Web Token",
                        "JSON Web Token",
                        "JavaScript Web Type",
                        "JSON With Token"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JSON Web Token"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which algorithm signs JWT?",
                    "options": [
                        "RSA",
                        "HMAC",
                        "Both",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Both"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "JWT has how many parts?",
                    "options": [
                        "2",
                        "3",
                        "4",
                        "5"
                    ],
                    "correct": "3"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "First part of JWT is?",
                    "options": [
                        "Header",
                        "Payload",
                        "Signature",
                        "Token"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Header"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Second part of JWT is?",
                    "options": [
                        "Payload",
                        "Header",
                        "Signature",
                        "Body"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Payload"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Third part of JWT is?",
                    "options": [
                        "Signature",
                        "Payload",
                        "Header",
                        "Footer"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Signature"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which header stores JWT?",
                    "options": [
                        "Auth",
                        "Authorization",
                        "Token",
                        "Access"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Authorization"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "Which HTTP code is unauthorized?",
                    "options": [
                        "401",
                        "403",
                        "404",
                        "500"
                    ],
                    "correct": "401"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which package generates JWT?",
                    "options": [
                        "jsonwebtoken",
                        "jwt",
                        "tokenizer",
                        "auth"
                    ],
                    "correct": "jsonwebtoken"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which is safer?",
                    "options": [
                        "Session",
                        "JWT",
                        "Cookies",
                        "Password"
                    ],
                    "correct": "JWT"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "id": "lesson20",
            "title": "lesson 20",
            "quiz": [
                {
                    "id": 1,
                    "question": "Which service is for static hosting?",
                    "options": [
                        "Firebase Hosting",
                        "MongoDB",
                        "MySQL",
                        "React"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Firebase Hosting"
                },
                {
                    "id": 2,
                    "question": "Which command deploys Firebase?",
                    "options": [
                        "firebase deploy",
                        "firebase start",
                        "firebase init",
                        "firebase push"
                    ],
                    "correct": "firebase deploy"
                },
                {
                    "id": 3,
                    "question": "Which platform hosts React apps?",
                    "options": [
                        "Vercel",
                        "Netlify",
                        "Firebase",
                        "All"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All"
                },
                {
                    "id": 4,
                    "question": "Which file defines Firebase config?",
                    "options": [
                        "firebase.json",
                        "config.js",
                        "setup.json",
                        "deploy.json"
                    ],
                    "correct": "firebase.json"
                },
                {
                    "id": 5,
                    "question": "Which service offers free SSL?",
                    "options": [
                        "Vercel",
                        "Netlify",
                        "Firebase",
                        "All"
                    ],
                    "correct": "All"
                },
                {
                    "id": 6,
                    "question": "Which command builds React app?",
                    "options": [
                        "npm run build",
                        "npm start",
                        "npm dev",
                        "npm react"
                    ],
                    "correct": "npm run build"
                },
                {
                    "id": 7,
                    "question": "Which is NOT a cloud provider?",
                    "options": [
                        "AWS",
                        "GCP",
                        "Azure",
                        "HTML"
                    ],
                    "correct": "HTML"
                },
                {
                    "id": 8,
                    "question": "CI/CD stands for?",
                    "options": [
                        "Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment",
                        "Code Integration/Code Delivery",
                        "Central Install/Cloud Deploy",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment"
                },
                {
                    "id": 9,
                    "question": "Which Firebase command initializes?",
                    "options": [
                        "firebase init",
                        "firebase deploy",
                        "firebase start",
                        "firebase config"
                    ],
                    "correct": "firebase init"
                },
                {
                    "id": 10,
                    "question": "Which is a containerization tool?",
                    "options": [
                        "Docker",
                        "Kubernetes",
                        "Both",
                        "None"
                    ],
                    "correct": "Both"
                }
            ]
        }
    ]
}